NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Handicapped (folder 4), 1976-1979 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  NYSUT position statements; State Education Department draft plan submitted under the Education for All Handicapped Children Act (P.L. 94-142), "Helping Children with Handicapping Conditions", c. 1978; amendments to Commissioner's Regulations, 1977; handwritten notes; related materials and correspondence
- Handicapping Meeting See also: Developmental Disabilities and Infant Mortality Prevention See also: Disabilities - Autism and Lovaas See also: Disabilities – Awarding High School Credit to Disabled See also: Disabilities – Effective Practices for Inclusive Programs See also: Disabilities – IDELR Highlights (Individuals with Disabilities Education Law Report), 1985 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  Discussion outline, "Meeting with Larry Gloekler Regarding the Draft New York State Plan for Educating Children with Handicapping Conditions by 1987-1989," prepared by NYSUT associate in educational services Patrick Flynn, December 1985; memo from NY State Education Department to school and district superintendents re space allocation for special education programs, June 1985
- Harris Poll See also: Survey (Box 30, Folder 3)
  Preliminary Report on the Issues Dividing NYSUT and NEA; preliminary report, NYSUT services; NYSUT correspondence re poll.
- Harris Poll, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  Background material for 1976 poll
- Harris Poll (folder 1), 1975 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  Harris Poll "Preliminary Report on the Issues Dividing NYSUT and NEA"; survey questions; tabulated results
- Harris Poll (folder 2), 1975 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  Preliminary results of Louis Harris and Associates, Inc., survey, "Attitudes of Upstate NYSUT Members and Local Presidents," October 1975; correspondence
- Health Care See: Home Health Care
- Helping Children at Risk See: Children at Risk
- Higher Education – Ad Hoc Organizing Committee to Save Public Higher Education, 1981 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  February 9, 1981. Flyer announcing organizing conference; NYSUT memo re creation of committee; NYSUT Information Bulletin re state budget
- Higher Education (folder 1), 1979-1980 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  State Education Department printed report, "The Regents Statewide Plan for the Development of Postsecondary Education,"1980; State Education Department discussion item to Regents, "Revised Standards for Registration of Postsecondary Curricula for General Purposes and for Professional Purposes," June 6, 1979; State Education Department discussion paper to Regents, "Comparison of Proposed Revisions in Regulations Governing Postsecondary Institutions," June 6, 1979; NYSUT correspondence
- Higher Education (folder 2), 1980 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  Memo from State Education Department to Chief Executive Officers of Postsecondary Institutions in New York State re implementation of new regulations on off-campus instruction, September 19; memos re financial aid; related correspondence
- Higher Education (folder 3), 1980 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  Memos as above
- Higher Education (folder 4), 1974-1978 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  Paper by James G. Ward, director of economic research, American Federation of Teachers, "Teachers, Professionalism, and Teacher Training," for presentation at the annual meeting of the American Educational Research Association, March 29, 1978, with cover note to NYSUT research director Charles Santelli; NYSUT comparison of three proposals for public funding of private higher education, November 10, 1977; NYSUT memo showing ten-year trend in state expenditures for public and private higher education, April 20, 1977; "Bundy Aid Program, 1969-1977: A Historical Report on New York State Colleges and Universities Receiving State Aid under Section 6401 of the Education Law," July 1977; Statement by Prof. Carol Brandon, first vice president, Professional Staff Congress/CUNY, to Assembly Higher Education Committee Hearing on Retrenchment, September 10, 1977; invitation to hearing from Assembly Higher Education Committee chair Melvin Miller, stating issue; presentation to Board of Regents Subcommittee on Higher Education by President Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., NYSUT, April 27, 1977; State Education Department report, "The Higher Educational System of New York State: A Summary of Major Changes in the State's Higher Educational System and Funding in Recent Years, March 1977; SUNY report, "College and University Degrees Conferred, 1975-1976"; related memos; press releases
- Higher Education (folder 5), 1973 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  Financial Statistics of Institutions of Higher Education for Fiscal Year Ending 1971, from U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare Office of Education; spreadsheets comparing salary distribution at CUNY and SUNY; other salary comparisons; Chronicle of Higher Education article re medical schools, January 14, 1974; NEA booklets, "Due Process and Tenure: Higher Education" and "Building Effective Locals in Higher Education"; information sheet, "The NEA and Higher Education"; statement by Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., co-president, NYSUT, at public hearing of the Joint Legislative Committee on Higher Education, April 3, 1973; confidential report, "The Management and Financing Colleges," Committee for Economic Development
- Higher Education (folder 6), 1971-1973 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  National Education Association memo to staff, updating on legislation, December 4, 1972; NEA memo to higher education activists, requesting advice on organizing strategy in light of "left/right" direction of competing unions AFT and AAUP, November 1, 1972; NEA memo to activists re Project GROW (Grass Roots Organizing Works), November 10, 1972; NEA memos and other materials re organizing at Temple University; NYSTA report based on data from American Association of University Professors, "1970-71 Average Compensation for Instructional Faculty at Selected Institutions on University, College and Junior College Levels"; statement by Emanuel Kafka, president, New York State Teachers Association, on Statewide Plan for the Expansion and Development of Higher Education, March 4, 1971; letter to Kafka from State Education Department requesting follow-up on comments; memo from Kafka to NYSTA colleague speculating on sincerity of request, April 26, 1971; press release from State of New York Executive Chamber announcing Gov. Nelson Rockefeller's appointment of Task Force to Study the Financing of Higher Education, October 7, 1972; newspaper clippings
- Higher Education Meeting, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  April 30, 1976. "Education in the 1976-77 Executive Budget: A Preliminary Report to the NYSUT Executive Committee," January 23, 1976; NYSUT report, "New York State Community Colleges Financial Statistics for 1974-75," March 1976; NYSUT memos re CUNY and SUNY funding in Executive Budget, percent of community college budget going to salaries
- Higher Education Speech – Governor's Task Force, 1976-1977 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  Draft discussion paper for AFT Advisory Commission on Higher Education, "Financing Higher Education: Basic Facts Underlying Current Issues," August 15, 1976; Statement before the Temporary State Commission on the Future of Postsecondary Education, by Ewald B. Nyquist, Commissioner of Education, January 6, 1977; Preliminary Estimates of Fall 1976 College and University Enrollments in New York State for SUNY, CUNY, and private institutions, with interpretive cover letter to NYSUT research director Charles Santelli, January 7, 1977
- Higher Education – Assembly Standing Committee Hearing, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  September 31, 1977. NYSUT memo re public hearing on retrenchment; handwritten notes
- Historical Analysis of Changes in Methods of Certifying Teachers in NYS, 1965 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  Doctoral dissertation by Vincent Gazzetta, State University of New York at Albany
- Hofstra, 1975-1982 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  Correspondence re survey of retired and active teachers in Nassau County, Long Island, re retirement issues, 1981-82; survey questions by NYSUT/Hofstra Teacher Center re teacher attitudes toward mainstreaming of "emotionally disturbed" students, 1981; governance agreement for teacher center, December 1975; related correspondence
- Home Health Care, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  NYSUT Report from the Task Force on Home Care Centers, April 1982
- Home Instruction, 1974-1987 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  Correspondence re parents' concerns about State Education Department testing proposals for children taught at home; text of three court cases, 1974, 1977, 1978
- Home Schooling See: Home Instruction
- Hoosick Falls Teachers Association, 1995 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  September 19, 1995. Flyer for rally, noting fourth year of working without a contract; talking points for rally; background sheet re "negotiations"; press release; NYS Public Employment Relations Board (PERB) fact-finding report between Hoosick Falls Central School District and teachers association, October 7
- HUMAN RELATIONS/Humanism/Human Rights/Civil Rights (used interchangeably) See also: Black Children See also: Conferences - Human Relations, Syracuse See also: Superintendent's Day
- Statewide Human Relations Coordinating Council/Committee, 1974 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  Two versions of Articles of Agreement, one for Statewide Human Relations Coordinating Council (with notation, "I can't think of a better name"), the other for Statewide Council for Humanism in Education, with differing objectives: humanism referring to general interpersonal relations, shared decision making; human relations meaning race relations
- Statewide Human Relations Coordination Committee, 1973 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  Correspondence questioning desirability of continued student attendance at conference, citing disruptive behavior, November-December 1973; minutes of meeting, including report of the Planning Subcommittee, September 21, 1973; minutes of May 18, with cover letter from chair Antonia Cortese; minutes of April 14; printed report of third annual conference, HR3, December 6-9, 1972; planning materials for fourth annual conference
- Human Relations Council, 1973 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  Outline of duties and structure of council; list of members; excerpt of Fleischmann Commission report re state training schools (incarceration facilities under prison system's Division for Youth) for troubled youth, with attached copy of letter to DFY director with questions for NEA survey and note to Antonia Cortese
- Human Relations Consultant Training, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 12)
  June 6-8, 1986. Facilitative correspondence re workshop on self-esteem and at-risk students; printout of consultants
- Human Relations Statewide Facilitator Training Conference, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 13)
  June 6-8, 1986. Agenda for workshop on at-risk students; newspaper clipping
- Human Relations Facilitators, 1985 (Box 31, Folder 14)
  September 18-20, 1985. Facilitative correspondence
- Human Relations Meetings, 1970-1974 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  Report and proposal to Statewide Human Relations Coordinating Committee meeting, June 11, 1974; conference reports; meeting agendas; correspondence
- Human Relations Meeting HR-4, 1973-1974 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  Correspondence; conference program and report; meeting minutes
- Human Relations (folder 1), 1971-1973 (Box 31, Folder 17)
  Hearings report of NYSTA Ad Hoc Committee on the Establishment of a Human Relations Council, October 15 and 25, 1971; Planning Committee meeting agendas; report of second annual conference (HR-2), 1971; human relations directory; correspondence
- Human Relations (folder 2), 1972-1975 (Box 31, Folder 18)
  Printed publications: "Teachers and Students: Report V: Mexican American Education Study: Differences in Teacher Interaction with Mexican American and Anglo Students," a report of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, March 1973; "Combating Discrimination in the Schools: Legal Remedies and Guidelines," a National Education Association publication, 1973; minor brochures; materials prepared by NEA Teacher Rights Program and U.S. Commission on Civil Rights: "Materials for School System and Association Racism Analysis," (no date).; report and program for third annual conference (HR-3)
- Center for Human Relations, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 19)
  Budget request; confidential memo re appointment of director; description of duties, with salary range; memos expressing concern over proposed salary compensation for director of human relations, out of line with established recommendations of Management Review Committee, April 28, 1992; chronology of initial operations of the center
- Center for Human Relations – Interview Session, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 20)
  April 14, 1972. List of candidates for director of the Center for Human Relations; related memos
- Center for Human Relations – Pending File – James Blair, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 21)
  Correspondence re job offer; resume; edited contract of employment; letter declining offer
- Center for Human Relations – James Doremus, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 22)
  Correspondence re interview for director position; resume, letters of reference; letter advising that James Blair had been hired
- Center for Human Relations – Paul Kane, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 23)
- Center for Human Relations – Donald Pierce, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 24)
  Correspondence re interview for director position; resume; letter advising that James Blair had been hired
- Center for Human Relations – Raymond Ratte, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 25)
- Center for Human Relations – David Simmons, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 26)
- Center for Human Relations – Walter Smith, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 27)
- Center for Human Relations – C. Dwayne Wilson, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 28)
  Correspondence re interview for director position; resume, letters of reference; letter advising that Dwayne's salary requirements far exceeded ability to meet
- Center for Human Relations – Eugene Zola, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 29)
- Committee on Civil and Human Rights, 1980 (Box 31, Folder 30)
  Minutes; 1979-80 year-end report
- Committee on Civil and Human Rights, 1977-1978 (Box 31, Folder 31)
  Correspondence; annual report, 1976-77
- Committee on Civil and Human Rights, 1975-1977 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  Minutes; annual report, 1976-77; report of Task Force on Affirmative Action and Leadership Development, 1976-77; Johns Hopkins University Center for Social Organization of Schools reports 230 and 231, July 1977, "Biracial Learning Teams and Race Relations in the Classroom: Four Field Experiments on Teams-Games-Tournament," and "Using Student Learning Teams to Desegregate"; NYSUT Report on Implementation of 1976 Resolutions
- NEA Human Relations Program Awards, 1973 (Box 32, Folder 2)
- Rosena J. Willis Award, 1973 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  Correspondence with Human Relations Committee and National Education Association (NEA); Equal Educational Opportunity (EEO) newsletter of New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA)
- James E. Allen Award, 1969-1973 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  Press release from NY State Education Department "Weissman Receives First Allen Memorial Award," April 27, 1973; list of candidates; guidelines and description of award by NYS Teachers Association (NYSTA), May 3, 1972; correspondence and notes re award, death of Allen; commemorative booklet, "James E. Allen, Jr.: From Elkins to Washington," honoring his accomplishments as Commissioner of NY State Education Department, 1969; newspaper clippings re death in airplane crash shortly after resigning from Nixon administration
- James E. Allen Nominations (Board of Regents), 1985 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  Nomination forms; narrative in support of Albert Shanker
- Martin Luther King Day, 1971 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  January 15, 1971. Newspaper clippings (New York Times); booklet on MLK distributed by National Education Association (NEA)
- Martin Luther King, Jr., 1995 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  April 12, 1995. Correspondence re meetings for NYS Martin Luther King, Jr. Institute for Nonviolence 1995 Ella Baker Academy Summer Residency Program for youth; handwritten notes
- Whitney M. Young, 1968-1971 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  Memorial program; schedule for funeral event; list of guests and official Washington delegation to funeral; speech by Young accepting Alfred E. Smith Award from New York State Teachers Association; letter from association to Young announcing award, September 16, 1968;newspaper clippings
- Humanism in Education See also: Black Children, 1973-1983 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  Printed reports, "The Human Family, Human Rights, and Peace: A Sourcebook for the Study and Discussion of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights: A Lay Version for the Common Man, Woman, and Child," Center for Teaching about Peace and War, Wayne State University (Detroit, MI), 1973; Report of a National Bilingual Bicultural Institute, "A Relook at Tucson '66 and Beyond," National Education Association, 1973; "School Community Relations Project: Four Workshops Designs for Improving Human Relations in the School Community," NYSUT, 1983; folder and materials for Human Relations conference, including description of humanistic education, 1980; correspondence re training programs in individual school districts
- Humanism in Education, 1975-1979 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  Memos, agendas, and meeting minutes from Antonia Cortese, chair of the Statewide Council for Humanism in Education, 1975; letter from State Education Department re Humanism in Education conference, 1975; summary of conference follow-up activities; evaluation forms; background description of Humanism in Education Project, 1976-1977; conference materials for individual districts re student discipline and other issues
- Conference on Humanism in Education, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  Full conference program and materials
- Conference on Humanism in Education – Registration and Financial, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  Registration and financial records
- Conferences – Financial Records, 1973 (Box 32, Folder 13)
  Bookkeeping logs, accounting statements, related memos; brochure, Current Interests of the Ford Foundation, 1976 and 1977
- Statewide Council for Humanism in Education Meeting, 1976 (Box 32, Folder 14)
  February 19, 1976. Correspondence between Education Commissioner Ewald Nyquist and NYSUT president Thomas Hobart re need to reconstitute Humanism in Education Program to better meet the needs of constituents, January 1976; meeting minutes, noting negative feedback from NYS School Boards Association
- Statewide Council for Humanism in Education, 1975-1976 (Box 32, Folder 15)
  Minutes of meetings, noting negative feedback; guidelines for consultants
- Statewide Council for Humanism in Education Sept.-Dec. 1975 (Box 32, Folder 16)
  Minutes of meetings, noting negative feedback; evaluation plan; district-level team evaluation questionnaires; correspondence
- Statewide Council for Humanism in Education April-June 1975 (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Humanizing Education Conference 1978 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  Brochures for eighth annual conference, sponsored by State Education Department, emphasizing arts in education; letter from NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese noting NYSUT's inability to send officers
- Discipline, 1976-1978 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  Report of the Human Rights Component of the "Easing Student Adjustment" Program funded by a grant of the Emergency School Aid Act, "Focus on Crisis Prevention: Manual for School Administrators and Student Activities Personnel," Board of Education of the City of New York, High School Division, August 1976; State Education Department memos to the Discipline Group, summarizing meetings of August 15, June 24, and November 9, 1977, and January 5, 1978; memo re guidelines for students rights and responsibilities, October 3, 1977; related materials
- Discipline Conference, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  February, 1979. Program abstract; letters of invitation; registration forms; lists of school districts
- Albany, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  November 16, 1979. Correspondence re human relations conference; Citizens for Better Schools proposal for increased parental involvement
- Averill Park, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  October 10, 1978. Workshop materials for human relations/humanistic education conference
- Brittonkill Human Relations Conference, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  November 21, 1979. Program and summary of feedback from human relations conference
- Burnt Hills, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  Outline for human relations conference; memos
- Byram Hills, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  Letter from teachers association president to NYSUT coordinator, noting relief that human relations conference was over, low teacher attendance but positive reaction; feedback forms
- Catskill, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  Human relations conference materials, including program, correspondence, handwritten notes
- Cazenovia, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  October 5, 1979. Program and related materials for communications conference; outline of problems particular to district; correspondence; handwritten notes
- Clarkstown Handicapped Conference, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  November 7, 1978. Program for superintendent's/human relations conference day, "Educating the Handicapped: It Takes More Than Love," November 7, 1978; related materials and correspondence
- Clarkstown, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 13)
  November 6, 1979. Materials for superintendent's/human relations conference day, "Working Together," re stereotyping; correspondence
- Erie BOCES II, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  March 14, 1980. Program for human relations conference
- Erie BOCES II, 1981 (Box 33, Folder 15)
  March 20, 1981. Program for human relations conference
- Grand Gorge, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 16)
  Correspondence re human relations conference; agenda; list of district's strengths and weaknesses
- Grand Island Discipline Conference, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 17)
  October 15, 1979. Correspondence re human relations conference on discipline; program; summation of group discussion
- Greene, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 18)
  Correspondence and agenda for human relations conference
- Kenmore Discipline Conference, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 19)
  Conference program; workshop descriptions; related materials
- Kenmore, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 20)
  March 14, 1980. Professional Development Day program
- Kenmore, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 21)
  April 21, 1978. Materials for human relations/communications conference; description of district and community; correspondence; 8-page list of feedback responses; copies of article about conference in NYSUT newsletter New York Teacher
- Middle Island Conference, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 22)
  November 4, 1980. Program for Teacher Conference Day, "Coping with Stress"; correspondence
- Mohawk-Herkimer Discipline Conference, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 23)
  May 22, 1979. Program for regional conference, "Positive Approaches to Student Discipline"
- New Lebanon, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 24)
  September 30, 1978. Community relations conference program; feedback forms with comments
- Newburgh Conference, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 25)
  March 6, 1978. Program for superintendent's day/human relations conference "Face to Face Communication"; summary of feedback comments; correspondence
- Newark Valley, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 26)
  February 14, 1980. Human relations conference program
- Onondaga Discipline Conference, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 27)
  May 23, 1979. Program for regional conference, "Positive Approaches to Student Discipline"
- Oswego Conferences, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 28)
  Correspondence re workshops on discipline for students and assertiveness for teachers
- Rensselaer, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 29)
  Program for discipline and human relations conference
- Richmondville, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 30)
  Agenda for humans relations conference
- Somers, 1978-1979 (Box 33, Folder 31)
  Correspondence re scheduling a human relations conference; notes about the district
- Syracuse, 1979 (Box 33, Folder 32)